Finding Aid for the Albert Boime Papers LSC.1834
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 3: Research materials, 1941-2008
  - Thomas Couture, bulk 1963-1977, 1949-1951, 1980s-2008
    - Thomas Couture miscellany, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      Correspondence regarding Couture image requests and notes for Bielefeld Lecture.
    - Couture miscellaneous, ca. 1968 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      Draft of "Thomas Couture: The Development of Painting in the Nineteenth Century," photographic prints, and galley proof of "Thomas Couture and the Evolution of painting in Nineteenth Century France."
    - Pifferaro, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Charles Gleyre, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      Correspondence regarding Gleyre illustrations, 4x5 transparency, notes, and copy of Gleyre painting. Folder originally titled Gleyre le Loup. See box 26 for additional research on Charles Gleyre.
    - Paul Delaroche, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
      Notes and photocopies. Some materials in German.
    - Robert Loftin Newman, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
      Notes and research file for article "Newman, Ryder, Couture And Hero-Worship in Art History."
    - Newman and Ryder, undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
      Articles, drafts of "Robert Loftin Newman, Thomas Couture, Albert Pinkham Ryder and the Problem of Artistic Obscurity," and notes.
    - Manet, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
      Photocopies. Materials are in French. See box 94 for additional research on Manet.
    - Manet and Puvis, undated (Box 16, Folder 13)
      Edited copy of "Chapter VII: The Academic Landscape: The Traditional Phase." Also includes pages from an untitled draft. See box 29 for additional research on Puvis de Chavannes and box 95 for additional research on Manet.
    - Puvis de Chavannes, ca. 1969 (Box 16, Folder 14)
      Notes, correspondence, article, and draft of "Chapter Four: Classicizing Painting" (unclear authorship). Some materials in French. See box 29 for additional research on Puvis de Chavannes.
    - Other pupils, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 15)
      Notes, photocopy, pages from untitled draft, and invoice.
    - Pupils, undated (Box 16, Folder 16)
      Annotated photocopies and notes (topics include Robert Loftin Newman).
    - Danish, ca. 1973 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Notes and a letter (related to Couture). Some materials in Danish.
    - Italian students, 1969-1970 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      Correspondence, notes, and annotated photocopies regarding Couture's Italian students. Some materials in French and Italian.
    - Eastern European students, 1969, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      Copies of images, correspondence, and notes.
    - English students, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      Correspondence and notes regarding Couture's English students.
    - Crowninshield Boston MFA, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous students, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
      Notes. Some materials in Italian.
    - Appraisals by Boime, 1969-1997 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      Appraisal requests and responses from Boime regarding specific Couture works. Correspondence regarding Couture paintings and works by his students. Folder contains some slides and original photographic material.
    - Couture appraisal, 2008 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      Correspondence with Gail Cooper, photographs, and documents regarding appraisal and painting condition.
    - Couture lecture, ca. 1988 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      Correspondence regarding Couture appraisal and note cards for lecture on Romans of the Decadence.
    - Correspondence 1949 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      Correspondence with Jerome Howe and copies of his notes on Couture. Some materials in French.
    - Correspondence 1950s (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence 1967-1969 (Box 17, Folder 12)
      Correspondence regarding Couture paintings. Some materials in French and German.
    - Correspondence 1970 (Box 17, Folder 13)
      Correspondence and invoices regarding Couture, Ryder, and Newman paintings. Some materials in French.
    - Correspondence 1971 (Box 17, Folder 14)
      Correspondence regarding Couture and William Babcock's Paintings. Some materials in French and German.
    - Correspondence 1972-1974 (Box 17, Folder 15)
      Correspondence regarding Couture, his students, and the Academy.
    - Correspondence 1975-1979 (Box 17, Folder 16)
      Correspondence regarding paintings by Couture and his students.
    - Correspondence 1980s (Box 17, Folder 17)
      Some materials in French and German.
    - Correspondence 1996 (Box 17, Folder 18)
      Correspondence regarding Thomas Couture paintings.
    - Correspondence, no date, undated (Box 17, Folder 19)
      Correspondence between Boime and Howe regarding Couture, his paintings, and his students.
    - Bertants Couture correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 17, Folder 20)
      Correspondence with Bertants Couture and some transcriptions. Correspondence from Jerome Howe. All materials are in French.
    - Preface, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
      Preface from "Thomas Couture and the Eclectic Vision."
    - Chapter I, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
      Chapter I: Eclecticism and the Society of the Juste Milieu from "Thomas Couture and the Eclectic Vision."
    - Chapter II notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
      Chapter II: Eclecticism and the Plastic Arts from "Thomas Couture and the Eclectic Vision."
  - Monuments and Icons, bulk 1988-1996, 2000-2007
    Boime's research on U.S. monuments and icons, likely for his publication "The Unveiling of the National Icons." The subseries includes a complete draft of "The Unveiling of the National Icons" as well as research on Gutzon Borglum and Mount Rushmore, the American flag, the Lincoln Monument, the Statue of Liberty, and the Flag-Raisers at Iwo Jima. Within these topics Boime collected a range of material including basic information about each monument as well as examples of this iconography or imagery being repurposed for other purposes. The file is arranged by type of material beginning with publication drafts and associated correspondence, and ending with research files. The research files are sub-organized by topic.
    - Unveiling of the National Icons (8 of 8), undated (Box 133, Folder 8)
      Galley proof from publisher for Boime's text "The Unveiling of the National Icons" with edits.
    - Icons - additions (1 of 2), 1994 (Box 134, Folder 1)
      Fellowship application materials for student Suzanne Loizeaux-Witte and paper "Struggle over Needs: Outline of a Socialist-Feminist Critical Theory of Late-Capitalist Political Culture" by Nancy Fraser. Folder also includes clippings, pages from draft on Statue of Liberty with edits, museum brochures, bibliography, and 4x5 transparencies.
    - Icons - additions (2 of 2), 1994 (Box 134, Folder 2)
    - National Icons - miscellaneous additions, 1994 (Box 134, Folder 3)
      Photocopies, clippings, notes, draft of paper on allegory, and correspondence.
    - Photo miscellaneous, 1993 (Box 134, Folder 4)
      Correspondence, illustration list, and clippings.
    - Icons, 1990-1991 (Box 134, Folder 5)
      Copies of photographs from National Archives and Records Administration of Lincoln Memorial, Washington Monument, and demonstrations at these sites. Notes, correspondence, comics, and book proposal for "Burn This Book" by Dread Scott.
    - Gutzon Borglum, 1990-1991 (Box 134, Folder 6)
      Notes, photocopies of newspaper articles regarding Sioux protests at Mt. Rushmore, correspondence, research materials, and drafts of "Gutzon Borglum's Mt. Rushmore Monument: Patriarchy Fixed in Stone."
    - Mount Rushmore Archives, 1990 (Box 134, Folder 7)
      Photocopies of correspondence from 1930s between Sioux representatives and a legal counselor and notes. Items presumably collected through archival research by Boime.
    - Flag, 1989-1991 (Box 135, Folder 1)
      Invoice, clippings, correspondence, exhibition packet from The New Museum of Contemporary Art for "Have You Attacked America Today?" Folder also includes table of contents and chapters from "True Blue-Constructing a National Identity" by Suzanne Loizeaux-Witte.
    - Lincoln, undated (Box 135, Folder 2)
      Notes, annotated photocopies, and 4x5 transparencies.
    - Lincoln monument, ca. 1993 (Box 135, Folder 3)
      Photocopies and clippings.
    - Iwo Jima Archives (1 of 2), 1992, 1996 (Box 135, Folder 4)
      Notes, clippings, photocopies, and student paper "Public Art and Bunker Hill" by Hiroko Shimizu. Other materials include notes, script for "Return to Iwo Jima" produced by Arnold Shapiro Productions, and Navy and Marine Corps documents regarding Iwo Jima.
    - Iwo Jima Archives (2 of 2), 1992, 1996 (Box 135, Folder 5)
    - Iwo Jima additions, bulk 1991-1992, 1996 (Box 135, Folder 6)
      Notes, newspaper index printouts, photocopies, correspondence, and issues of "Fortitudine" (newsletter of the Marine Corps Historical Program).
    - Vietnam, ca. 1994 (Box 135, Folder 7)
      Clippings, photocopies, and notes.
    - Draft: Unveiling of the National Icons, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
      Bound draft of "The Unveiling of the National Icons" with substantial edits throughout.
    - Unveiling of the National Icons 1, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
      Complete draft of "Introduction" and "Chapter II, The Engendering of Moderate Politics: The Statue of Liberty" for "The Unveiling of the National Icons: A Plea for Patriotic Iconoclasm in a Nationalist Era" with edits. Folder also includes 1 page of notes.
    - Unveiling of the National Icons 2, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
      Manuscript draft of Chapter I, Patriotism and Protest: Reconstituting Old Glory, for "The Unveiling of the National Icons."
    - Unveiling of the National Icons 3, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
      Draft of "Chapter III-Patriarchy Fixed in Stone: Gutzon Borglum's Mt. Rushmore" for "The Unveiling of the National Icons" with edits.
    - Unveiling of the National Icons 4, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Draft of "Chapter IV-The Battle for Hearts and Minds: The Marine Corps Memorial" for "The Unveiling of the National Icons" with edits.
    - Unveiling of the National Icons 5, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
      Draft of "Chapter V, A House Divided Cannot Stand: The Recuperation of the Lincoln Memorial," for "The Unveiling of the National Icons," with edits throughout. Pages are out of order.
    - Unveiling of the National Icons 6, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
      Two copies of draft of "Epilogue-Vietnam Veterans Memorial" for "The Unveiling of the National Icons."
    - Unveiling of the National Icons 7, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
      Draft of Appendix I and III with notes for "The Unveiling of the National Icons."
    - Unveiling of the National Icons (1 of 8), undated (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Unveiling of the National Icons (2 of 8), undated (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Unveiling of the National Icons (3 of 8), undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Unveiling of the National Icons (4 of 8), undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Unveiling of the National Icons (5 of 8), undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Unveiling of the National Icons (6 of 8), undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Unveiling of the National Icons (7 of 8), undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Chapter II, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      Photocopies and correspondence.
    - IV, 1994 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      Invoice and copies of co-opted images of Iwo Jima flag-raising.
    - Icons - Chapter V, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
      Complete draft of "Chapter V: The Recuperation of the Lincoln Memorial."
    - Brand new icon, 1996-1997 (Box 19, Folder 8)
      Clippings, correspondence, notes, and photocopies.
    - National Icons, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
      Pages from draft of "The Unveiling of the National Icons: Patriotic Iconoclasm in a Nationalist Era."
    - National Icons, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 10)
      Photocopied images of US national icons.
    - Newspaper insert, 1991 (Box 19, Folder 11)
      Newspaper insert from LA X-Press featuring creative uses of the American flag. Also includes a 4 x 5 transparency.
    - Unveiling - readers reports, 1994-1995 (Box 19, Folder 12)
      Lillian Vernon catalog, notes, and reports and reviews of Boime's work "The Unveiling of the National Icons."
    - Illustrations, undated (Box 19, Folder 13)
      Illustration list of one of Boime's books, presumably "The Unveiling of the National Icons."
    - Additional photos - Icons, 1993-1995 (Box 19, Folder 14)
      Correspondence, photos of Washington National Monuments, clippings, and photocopies.
    - Miscellaneous photos icons, undated (Box 19, Folder 15)
      Clippings and political cartoons featuring national monuments.
    - New additions, 1996, 2004 (Box 19, Folder 16)
      Photocopies of newspaper articles about controversial art exhibit and clippings.
    - More additions - Icons, undated (Box 19, Folder 17)
      Photocopies, notes, and bibliography.
    - National Icons miscellaneous, bulk 1991, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 18)
      Clippings, correspondence, notes, image requests, and student paper by Richard Iosty "The AIDS Memorial Quilt: Mourning, Activism, and the Politics of Sentimentality."
    - Permissions, 1992-1995 (Box 19, Folder 19)
      Correspondence regarding photo/image permissions and invoices.
    - Permissions sent, 1993-1994 (Box 19, Folder 20)
      Correspondence regarding photo/image permissions.
    - Miscellaneous permissions, 1990-1991, 1996 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      Correspondence, invoices, and clippings.
    - New permissions, 1993, 1996 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Publication correspondence, bulk 1994-1996, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 3)
      Correspondence regarding photo permissions and other publication details for "The Unveiling of the National Icons."
    - Public art, 1991-1992 (Box 20, Folder 4)
      Notes, photocopies, proposal, slides, and correspondence from Audrey Flack. Folder also includes University of Manitoba course materials and an application for historic sculpture designation for Pershing Square statuary.
    - Monumental sculpture, ca. 1991 (Box 20, Folder 5)
      Bibliography, notes, photocopy, student paper, article, and syllabus for unidentified course.
    - Monuments, ca. 1990 (Box 20, Folder 6)
      Proposal, student paper, and photocopies.
    - Monuments II, 2001 (Box 20, Folder 7)
      Draft of "War and Peace and Clay: A Tribute to World War II Veterans" (authorship unclear) and student paper "Playing with Play: The Appropriation of Children's Activities, Symbols, and Play" by Ali Conklyn.
    - Monument images, undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
      Photocopies of images for Boime's volume on national icons.
    - Photos, 1993-1994 (Box 20, Folder 9)
      Photocopies, clippings, and 4x5 transparency
    - Borglum film interview, 2007 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      Correspondence, script, and travel itinerary for filmed interview for "History Detectives" regarding Borglum and Mount Rushmore.
    - Borglum, undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
      Notes and draft of "Gutzon Borglum's Mt. Rushmore Monument: Patriarchy Fixed in Stone."
    - Rushmore additions, 1991, 1995, 1998 (Box 21, Folder 3)
      Photocopies, promotional materials from Mount Rushmore Preservation Fund, book featuring "The Me Collection" by Neil Grayson, correspondence, and copy of IF Magazine from March-April 1998.
    - Mount Rushmore, 1990-1991 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      Notes, correspondence, and photocopies of images of Mount Rushmore with illustration lists for Boime's publication. Folder also includes 4x5 transparencies, drafts of "Gutzon Borglum's Mt. Rushmore Monument: Patriarchy Fixed in Stone," and Mt. Rushmore brochures and tourist literature.
    - Mount Rushmore II, 1987, 1991 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      Photocopies from DeKalb Historical Society, drafts of "Gutzon Borglum's Mt. Rushmore Monument: Patriarchy Fixed in Stone," correspondence, clippings, notes, and inquiries regarding the Ku Klux Klan and Borglum.
    - Flag, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      Catalog of selected artworks by African American artists, photocopies, correspondence, 4x5 transparency, and draft of "Waving the Red Flag and Reconstituting Old Glory" with edits.
    - Flag additions, 1991 (Box 21, Folder 7)
      Clippings, photocopies, and copy of University of Miami Law Review Volume 45 from September 1990, Number 1.
    - Flag permission, 1990, 1993 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      Correspondence regarding photo/image permissions, clippings, and catalog of American flag paintings by Howard Finster.
    - Miscellaneous flag and Lincoln, 1993 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Ebony - Lincoln 1963, ca. 1992 (Box 21, Folder 10)
      Bibliography and photocopies about monuments.
    - Statue of Liberty, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
      Conference paper "Western Theory and Chinese Reality" by Shang Longxi featuring elements on Statue of Liberty, and photocopies.
    - Statue of Liberty, 1985, 1988 (Box 22, Folder 2)
      Student paper "The Lincoln Memorial" by Patricia I. Carranza and Michael Edelstein. Also includes correspondence and notes.
    - Statue of Liberty, 1991-1992 (Box 22, Folder 3)
      Clippings, photocopies, notes, and student paper "Appropriate Protest at the Statue of Liberty: Appropriation Through Action."
    - Statue of Liberty, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      Brochures and chronology of Statue of Liberty, notes, and Long Range Interpretive Plan for Statue of Liberty National Monument.
    - Statue of Liberty, undated (Box 22, Folder 5)
      Notes and annotated photocopies.
    - Statue of Liberty redux, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 6)
      Travel correspondence, invoices, photocopied articles, and correspondence regarding a collaborative project on the Statue of Liberty between the National Park Service and the Organization of American Historians.
    - The black Statue of Liberty rumor, 2000 (Box 22, Folder 7)
      Report "The Black Statue of Liberty Rumor: An Inquiry into the History and Meaning of Bartholdi's Liberte eclairant le Monde" by Rebecca M. Joseph.
    - Statue of Liberty, 1997 (Box 22, Folder 8)
      Postcard, American Airlines napkins and placemat--all carrying Statue of Liberty iconography.
    - Iwo Jima, 1995 (Box 22, Folder 9)
      Brochures for Iwo Jima Memorial Monument, clippings from New York Times, photos of Iwo Jima memorial, correspondence, Iwo Jima Survivors Journal, and journal of George G. Gentile (Iwo Jima Survivor).
    - Kyoto Arashiyama Museum, 1991 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      Images, photos, and museum catalog of materials related to Iwo Jima from Kyoto Arashiyama Museum. Materials in Japanese.
    - The flag raisers, 1991 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      Photocopies of articles regarding Iwo Jima flag raisers and correspondence with various historical societies. A large portion of research in this folder is related to flag raiser Ira Hayes and the Pima Indians.
    - Japanese perspective, 1991 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      Photocopies, clippings, notes, and political cartoons. Some materials in Japanese.
    - Indian and Japanese issues, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      Correspondence, clippings, and notes. Folder also includes dissertation prospectus "An Investigation of the 'Exceptional:' Women's Involvement in Sculptural Production in Late Nineteenth Century Paris" by Anastasia Easterday and student paper "Monumental Sculpture" by Beth Reuter.
    - Lavoie 9/11, 2003 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      Notes, paper by Boime "Can There be Art History After the Trade Towers?" and e-mail correspondence with Vincent Lavoie.
    - Lavoie 9/11, 2003 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      Correspondence with Vincent Lavoie regarding Boime's interest in the image-memorialization of the Twin Towers after 9/11. Folder also includes a publication contract between Le Mois de la Photo a Montreal and Boime.
  - Assorted Artists, 1972-2008
    Boime's research on a variety of artists. Most of the materials incorporated here did not result in a publication included with the files or did not constitute a large enough volume of material to be considered a separate subseries. Much of this research may have contributed to Boime's Social History of Modern Art series. The files are arranged alphabetically by artist's last name.
    - William Blake and the Lunar Society, undated (Box 136, Folder 1)
      Notes, photocopies, Italian newsletter, student paper "The Lunar Society as Patrons of the Arts" by Christin Mamiya, and miscellaneous pages to untitled draft. Folder also includes pages from drafts of papers on Henry Fuseli, William Blake, Robert Fulton, Thomas Hope, and John Flaxman. Topics include the Industrial Revolution.
    - 18th century and William Blake, undated (Box 136, Folder 2)
      Art History 127 syllabi and notes (topics include Blake and Greuze).
    - Revelation of Modern Art - notes (1 of 2), undated (Box 136, Folder 3)
      Copy of "Modern Thought and Catholicism" by Paul Gauguin (translated and annotated by Frank Lester Pleadwell)--versions in French and English with notes by Boime.
    - Revelation of Modern Art - notes (2 of 2), undated (Box 136, Folder 4)
    - Notes on Ingres (1 of 2), 1975, 1979 (Box 136, Folder 5)
      Correspondence and photocopies.
    - Paul Klee, undated (Box 136, Folder 6)
      Notes and photocopy. Folder includes article "Klee's 'Letter Ghost'" by Elizabeth Pess.
    - Egypt report, undated (Box 136, Folder 7)
      Photocopies of report on Egypt. According to note in file, materials relate to Marisol.
    - Thomas Satterthwaite Noble (1 of 3), ca. 1987 (Box 136, Folder 8)
      Notes, correspondence, photocopies, and draft of exhibition catalog. See box 97 for additional research on this topic.
    - Thomas Satterthwaite Noble (2 of 3), ca. 1987 (Box 136, Folder 9)
    - Thomas Satterthwaite Noble (3 of 3), ca. 1987 (Box 136, Folder 10)
    - Pablo Picasso, 1973 (Box 137, Folder 1)
      Correspondence, chronology, notes (topics include Newman-Ryder), and photocopies.
    - Piero della Francesca (1 of 2), ca. 1992 (Box 137, Folder 2)
      "Piero and His Legacy" conference materials from the National Gallery of Art, maps, brochures, list of conference registrants, draft of "Piero and the Two Cultures, clippings, photocopies, notes, and chronology of Piero Della Francesca.
    - Piero della Francesca (2 of 2), ca. 1992 (Box 137, Folder 3)
    - Albert Pinkham Ryder (1 of 2), ca. 1986-1993 (Box 137, Folder 4)
      Notes, drafts of lecture "Ryder on a Gilded Horse", annotated photocopies, photos, 4x5 negatives, and correspondence. Folder also includes a draft of a paper by Lloyd Goodrich entitled "Albert Pinkham Ryder: The Man and His Art."
    - Albert Pinkham Ryder (2 of 2), ca. 1986-1993 (Box 137, Folder 5)
    - Notes on Ingres (2 of 2), 1975, 1979 (Box 147, Folder 3)
    - Photocopied images, ca. 1987 (Box 147, Folder 4)
      Image request form and photocopies of work by Albert Pinkham Ryder.
    - William Blake, 1972 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      Notes and photocopies about William Blake. Folder includes draft of a paper on Blake, though it is unclear whether the paper was authored by Boime or Dr. Moore.
    - Anthony Blunt, bulk 2002, 1979 (Box 23, Folder 8)
      Newspaper article on "The Blunt Case," correspondence from Andrew Brainerd, and text from Commentary magazine.
    - Louis Leopold Boilly, 1991-1992 (Box 23, Folder 9)
      Correspondence, notes, 4x5 negatives, drafts of speech, and article entitled "Louis Boilly's Reading of the XIth and XIIth Bulletins of the Grande Armee."
    - William Bouguereau, 1986 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      Student papers "William Bouguereau In Perspective" by Lilian Staple, "The Bouguereau Movement is Back" by Irina Costache, "Bouguereau's Pastorale, In France and in America" by Patricia McGinn, and "Bouguereau and the Late Nineteenth Century American Collector" by William Steinway. File originally titled Boogie.
    - William Bouguereau, bulk 1975-1978, 1986 (Box 24, Folder 2)